Finding Aid for Arthur Scott Aiton Papers, 1922-1959
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur Scott Aiton papers 1922-1959
Aiton, Arthur Scott, 1894-1955.
1 linear feet
85852 Aa 2
Professor of Latin American history at the University of Michigan. Correspondence concerning his professional and personal activities; also class outlines, bibliographies, term papers, and examinations; and manuscripts of books and articles, notes and transcribed documents relating to colonial Latin America.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Arthur S. Aiton (donor no. 2468 ) and came to the library in multiple accession beginning in 1954.
The collection is open to research.
Arthur S. Aiton was born in Alameda, California, on April 15, 1894. He attended the University of California, receiving three degrees (AB, 1916; AM, 1918; PhD, 1923). He joined the history department of the University of Michigan as an instructor in 1921. He became an assistant professor in 1923, associate profess in 1926, and professor in 1929.
Aiton was an expert on Hispanic-American history and an acknowledged authority on the sixteenth century Conquistadores. His research illuminated the Coronado expedition across the American Southwest. His most notable book was Antonio de Mendoza, First Viceroy of New Spain. He was working on a history of Latin America at the time of his death.
During World War II, he was director of the U.S. Army Latin-American Area Training Program at the University of Michigan.
Professor Aiton died December 29, 1955.
The collection includes correspondence, professional papers relating to his teaching, research, and university activities, and manuscripts of his writings, both published and unpublished.
Subjects:
Aiton, Arthur Scott, 1894-1955.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Senate.; United States. Office of Strategic Services.; World War, 1939-1945.; Historians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Barnes, Walter, 1880-; Bining, Arthur Cecil, 1893-1957.; Bolton, Herbert Eugene, 1870-1953.; Borah, Woodrow Wilson, 1912-; Boyce, Gray Cowan, 1899-1981.; Cleven, N. Andrew N. (Nels Andrew Nelson), 1874-1961.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Donovan, William J. (William Joseph), 1883-1959.; Hanke, Lewis Ulysses, 1905-; Haring, C. H. (Clarence Henry), 1885-1960.; Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.; King, James Ferguson, 1913-1983.; Martin, John Butlin, 1909-; Merriman, Roger Bigelow, 1876-1945.; Nevins, Allan, 1890-1971.; Nowell, Charles E.; Parry, J. H. (John Horace), 1914-1982.; Priestley, Herbert Ingram, 1875-1944.; Rippy, J. Fred (James Fred), 1892-1977.; Robertson, James Alexander, 1873-1939.; Shiels, W. Eugene (William Eugene), 1897-; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; Wagner, Henry Raup, 1862-1957.; Whitaker, Arthur Preston, 1895-1979.; Wilgus, A. Curtis (Alva Curtis), 1897-1981.; Wright, Irene Aloha, 1879-1972.; Zavala, Silvio Arturo, 1909-2014.
- Correspondence
  - 1922-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1942 (Box 1)
  - 1943-1946 (Box 1)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - 1949-1959 undated (Box 1)
- Other papers
  - Senate Advisory Committee of the University of Michigan minutes 1937-1942 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Term papers on Latin American history, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies of Latin American history (Box 1)
  - Class outlines and sample examinations (Box 1)
  - Speeches on Latin America, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Notes, articles and documents on New Spain in the 16th Century, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - "Dongan's Counter Jesuit Policy" (fragmentary) (Box 1)
  - "Ideas on the Church-State Problem in 19th Century Latin America"; also British activities in the Spanish colonies in the early 19th century (fragmentary) (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning the development of the University of Mexico (Box 1)
- Manuscripts of writings
  - Manuscript of book, "Viceroy Luis de Velasco, the Elder", 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of The Rise of the Latin American Nations, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of book on Viceroy Antonio de Mendoza (fragmentary) (Box 1)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Barnes, Walter, 1880-
March 11, 1938
Bining, Arthur Cecil, 1893-1957.
1950-1951
Bolton, Herbert Eugene, 1870-1953.
May 5, 1927, Nov. 5, 1931, Nov. 8, 1935, May 22, 1936, Sept. 4, 1945, Aug. 30, 1950, and undated
Borah, Woodrow Wilson, 1912-
Dec. 27, 1938
Boyce, Gray Cowan, 1899-1981
July 3, 1949
Cleven, N. Andrew N. (Nels Andrew Nelson), 1874-1961
July 27, 1937
Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.
Dec. 30, 1940
Donovan, William J. (William Joseph), 1883-1959.
Jan. 21, 1946
Hanke, Lewis Ulysses, 1905-
June 10, 1948, and May 25, 1949
Haring, C. H. (Clarence Henry), 1885-1960.
Jan. 5, 1933
Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.
Jan. 26, 1942 and Jan. 31, 1942
King, James Ferguson, 1913-1983
Feb. 1, 1946, Feb. 11, 1946, Aug. 22, 1946, and June 1, 1949
Martin, John Butlin, 1909-
Dec. 2, 1950
Merriman, Roger Bigelow, 1876-1945.
Dec. 2, 1924, and Apr. 22, 1927
Nevins, Allan, 1890-1971.
Undated
Nowell, Charles E.
Feb. 9, 1950
Parry, J. H. (John Horace), 1914-1982
Jan. 17, 1938
Priestley, Herbert Ingram, 1875-1944.
Feb. 12, 1925
Rippy, J. Fred (James Fred), 1892-1977.
May 13, 1930 and Dec. 6, 1930
Robertson, James Alexander, 1873-1939.
Dec. 3, 1929
Shiels, W. Eugene (William Eugene), 1897-
Sept. 25, 1941 and Dec. 15, 1951
Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.
Mar. 14, 1952
Wagner, Henry Raup, 1862-1957.
Aug. 31, 1942, Nov. 13, 1942, Dec. 1942
Whitaker, Arthur Preston, 1895-1979
Dec. 14, 1939
Wilgus, A. Curtis (Alva Curtis), 1897-1981.
July 7, 1928
Wright, Irene Aloha, 1879-1972.
Dec. 9, 1929, and Jan. 17, 1940
Zavala, Silvio Arturo, 1909-2014
Dec. 3, 1939